Riley mss. V, 1876-1917 LMC 1888
Lilly Library
Riley mss. V
1876-1917
Lilly Library
Riley, James Whitcomb, 1849-1916
LMC 1888
6 linear feet 6 boxes
The Riley mss. V, 1876-1917, consist of the correspondence and writings of James Whitcomb Riley, 1849-1916, poet, born in Greenfield, Indiana. He later lived on Lockerbie Street in Indianapolis, Indiana.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
James Whitcomb Riley, 1849-1916, was an Indiana poet known for his children's poetry and works in dialect.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Children's Letters, Miscellaneous, Printed, Photographs, Writings, and Copies.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondents in the collection are: Isaac E. Adams, Edward Jay Allen, Young Ewing Allison, John M. Anderson, Marie Louise (Newland) Andrews, Clara (Rogers) Arnold, Thomas B. Arnold, Lulu Atkison, B.F. Aydelott, George Milroy Bailey, Frank Tarkington Baker, Faith Baldwin, Katherine (Willard) Baldwin, John Kendrick Bangs, D.A. Barrackman, Josephine Bartholomew, Truman Howe Bartlett, Esther Bealle, Henry Augustin Beers, Rebecca Katharine Beeson, Bessie Bell, Joseph E. Bell, James Berry Bensel, Mrs. Riley Maria Fletcher Berry, James Buckley Black, Eliza Ann (Cooper) Blaker, Willis Stanley Blatchley, Harry Barton Bogg, Lilian Lida (Bell) Bogue, Edward William Bok, William J. Bok, Charles Hull Botsford, John Eliot Bowen, Alembert Winthrop Brayton, Nelson Dewes Brayton, Bertha R. Briggs, John C. Briggs, Earl Alonzo Brinninstool, Charles R. Brodix, George Brown, George Pliny Brown, J. Burgess Brown, William Eugene Brown, Cora Matilda Bryan, Clarence Clough Buel, Jerry Bundy, Clara (Bradley) Burdette, Robert Jones Burdette, Edward Livermore Burlingame, Frances Eliza (Hodgson) Burnett, Asa W. Burrows, Mahlon O. Butler, Frank Willoughby Butterworth, Mildred L. (Harris) Camp, Mary (Stewart) Carey, William Carey, Emma Shields (Nunemacher) Carleton, George A. Carr, Fred Hayden Carruth, Elizabeth York Case, Kate M. Cathcart, Madison Julius Cawein, David Laurance Chambers, Samuel Austin Chapin, Mary (Knippenberg) Chapman, Maud M. Charlton, Thomas Jefferson Charlton, Charles F. Chicester, Howard Chandler Christy, John Cecil Clay, Charles H. Clough, Irwin Shrewsbury Cobb, John Albert Cockerill, Emma Cole, Schuyler Colfax, Hannah L. Collins, Russell Herman Conwell, Nellie (Millikan) Cooley, Bertha L. Corbett, T.J. Cullen, John Jay Curtis, Thomas Augustine Daly, Charles Anderson Dana, Eugene C. Dana, F.E.C. Dana, Edward Daniels Elise (Wills) Darlington, Frank Graef Darlington, J. Howard Davis, Richard Lew Dawson, Katharine (Huntington) Day, Irene De Bitt, Charles Deering, Mary Felix De Moville, John Marcus Dickey, Rochelle Dietz, L.M. Dillman, May (Winters) Donnan, A.H. Dooley, James Oscar Greeley Duffy, Clara Anita Dyer, Maud G. Early, Samuel Evingston Earp, The Edward MacDowell Memorial Association, Alanson W. Edwards, Edmund Henry Eitel, Elva May (Riley) Eitel, Henry Eitel, William DeLancey Ellwanger, William J. Ethell, Francis Anson Evans, Harmon J. Everett, Edward S. Fagg, Charles Warren Fairbanks, De Verne Fargo, Charles Wells Farnham, Effie L. Fentress, Mrs. Carl T. Fischer, Herbert Willard Foltz, Henry James Forman, Ralph F. Forman, Sam Walter Foss, William Dudley Foulke, William F. Fox, Edward Freiberger, Anne Hathaway French, Anne Richmond (Warner) French, Hector Fuller, Lucy Salome Furman, Norman Rowland Gale, William Wilson Galt, Robert Wason Geiger, David Gibson, William Thomas Giffe, Jeannette Leonard Gilder, Richard Watson Gilder, Lloyd Goble, Isaac Pusey Gray, Marion Hunter (Weinstein) Gray, Pierre Gray, Hiram M. Greene, Gridiron Club, Richard Buchner Gruelle, Theodosia Haine, Emma S. Haldeman, Albert James Halford, Elijah Walker Halford, Gilbert Edgerton Hall, Arthur Clinton Hamilton, Esther (LaRose) Harris, Evelyn Harris, Francis Augustine Harris, Joel Chandler Harris, Julia Florida (Collier) Harris, Julian LaRose Harris, Fred W. Hathaway, Willis Brooks Hawkins, Franklin Busch Hays, Franklin W. Hays, Louella Graves (White) Hays, Thomas Whitcomb Hays, William Shakespeare Hays, Frank Glover Heaton, William Alexander Heckard, Grace (McKinley) Heidt, Belle Heilman, Ean Boyd Heiney, Robert D. Heinl, Caroline Butler Hendricks, Eldo Lewis Hendricks, Charlotte Herbrue, James A. Herne, Henry A. Hersey, Nelson Hersh, Helene Hibben, Janie K. Hibben, Katherine (Lemcke) Hicks, George Cooper Hitt, Laura (Fletcher) Hodges, Leigh Mitchell Hodges, Laurence Curran Hodgson, Charles Louis Holstein, Frederick Mercer Hopkins, Alfred Edward Hostelley, Emerson Hough, William A. Hough, Richard Hovey, Timothy Edward Howard, Will David Howe, Hewitt Hanson Howland, Earl Hudelson, Rupert Hughes, Thomas Hutchinson, Edith Ivor-Parry, John Jack, Mary Booth (Tarkington) Jameson, Effie Elliott (Johnston) Jenkins, Thomas Spencer Jerome, Robert Underwood Johnson, Henry Johnstone, Elizabeth (Voorhees) Jones, Richard Lloyd Jones, Rosaline (Ewan) Jones, Samuel Milton Jones, David Starr Jordan, Dulcina (Mason) Jordan, Wilbur Jones Kay, Ezra Fremont Kendall, James M. Kerr, Mary (Perry) King, Leslie Kinnard, Luella S. Kinnard, William J. Kinsley, Samuel Ellsworth Kiser, Frank E. Knight, Joseph Knight, Will Knippenberg, William C. Knocke, Herman A. Kretschmar, John Lambert, George Lassar, Clara Elizabeth Laughlin, Frank Lawson, Harvey Porter Layton, Albert Lee, Homer Lee, James Wideman Lee, Cornelia (Cunningham) Lemcke, Amy Leslie, Albert Lieber, Oliver E. Linton, John Uri Lloyd, George Browning Lockwood, Lula Maye Lockwood, William E. Lockwood, Nellie Robinson Loehr, Charles James Longman, Robert Louthean, Edward Verrall Lucas, Robert Montford Lucky, Henry Clay Lukens, James MacArthur, Daniel Macfauley, John Ernest McCann, Samuel Sidney McClure, Mary Catherine MacDonald, Walter Hugh McDougall, Burr William McIntosh, Robert McIntyre, Jesse McKinney, William L. Maclean, J.H. Madden, Nellie C. Magennis, C.H. Mansfield, Alden March, William Matthew Marine, Sister Mary Rose, Walt Mason, James Newton Matthews, Madaline Matthews, Constance Elizabeth Maud, Leon Mead, Edith Thomas Medairy, Nina T. Medairy, Nellie (Simmons) Meier, Rilla (Beeber) Meyer, Alice Christiana (Thompson) Meynell, DeWitt Miller, Melville Winans Miller, Oscar L. Miller, John Fowler Mitchell, Mary (Cadwalader) Mitchell, Silas Weir Mitchell, Michael Monahan, Harriet Monroe, Charles Washington Moores, Merrill Moores, Frank Marion Morris, Edwin Wilson Morse, Louise (Chandler) Moulton, Richard Kendall Munkittrick, Emma (Roberts) Nash, Elizabeth Rowena (McRae) New, Harry Stewart New, Anna Nichols, Meredith Nicholson, Benjamin Northrop, Carrie Maria (Wilson) Nye, Elizabeth Mitchell (Loring) Nye, Frank Mellen Nye, John C. Ochiltree, Mena Kemp Ogan, John Boyle O'Reilly, Duffield Osborne, Marian (Heinly) Page, Walter Hines Page, Daniel L. Paine, Russell Palmer, Benjamin Strattan Parker, Beatrice (Crawford) Parkyns, Margaret (Guffin) Parry, Thomas Wood Parry, Gavin Lodge Payne, Thomas Brower Peacock, Bernadotte Perrin, Fred Riley Persons, Edward Sievers Peterson, Sophia Emilia (Linsley) Phelps, William Lyon Phelps, George Morris Philips, John Sanburn Phillips, Don Piatt, John James Piatt, Thomas M. Pletcher, Mary (Wimborough) Ploughe, James Burton Pond, Henry Goslee Prout, Frank Arthur Putnam, William Emory Quinby, Samuel Moffett Ralston, Daniel Moore Ransdell, Mary (Cathcart) Ransdell, Laura Ream, Lorena (Nave) Redding, Jean Redman, Redpath Lyceum Bureau, Ellen Louise (Lyon) Reed, Myron Winslow Reed, Stuart Felix Reed, Whitelaw Reid, James Whitcomb Reilly, Charles M. Relyea, Alva O. Reser, Alonzo Leora Rice, J. de Forrest Richards, Louise (Parks) Richards, George Riddle, John Clark Ridpath, James Whitcomb Riley, John Andrew Riley, Julia (Wilson) Riley, Martin Whitten Riley, Hallie Erminie Rives, Ella May (White) Robinson, Josephine Robinson, Mary Yandes Robinson, William B. Rodgers, Horace E. Rood, Frances (MacIntire) Ross, Henry C. Ryan, Mary Joanna Safford, Mary Augusta C. Salmond, Francis Henry Saltus, Cora Belle Schnee, Frank Hall Scott, Arthur Hawley Scribner, Scribner, firm, publishers, Elizabeth (Cochrane) Seaman, Selig Polyscope Company, May (Wright) Sewall, Julia Graydon Sharpe, George Doublass Sherley, Chesla Clella Sherlock, Frank Dempster Sherman, William Edward Simonds, Wesley Sisson, John J. Skinner, Otis Skinner, David C. Smith, George C. Smith, William Henry Smith, Wyckliffe Smith, George Southard, Mary Angela Spink, Burt C. Stephenson, Antoinette Sterling, Adlai Ewing Stevnson, Fanny (Van de Grift) Stevenson, William Frederic Stilz, Joseph Marshall Stoddart, Bram Stoker, Anson Phelps Stokes, Melville Elijah Stone, Juliet Virginia (Humphries) Strauss, James Flynn Stutesman, Marthena (Funkhouser) Swafford, Delight Sweetser, Clara Moyse Tadlock, Myrtle Catherine Tallman, James Tanner, Booth Tarkington, John Stevenson Tarkington, William Simeon Reeves Tarkington, Minnetta Theodora Taylor, Edith Matilda Thomas, W.O. Thomas, Alice (Lee) Thompson, Slason Thompson, Will Henry Thompson, Martha A. Barr Totten, Mira Troth, George Crouse Tyler, Henry Tyrrell, Alicia (Keisker) Van Burne, Albert Ferguson Vandegrift, W. Horace Varney, Clara Vawter, John William Vawter, William Henry Venable, H. Karl Volland, Phillip Vollmer, James Paxton Voorhees, Lillian (Harris) Wagener, Amos J. Walker, Barclay Walker, James Joseph Walsh, Harry Franklin Waltman, William H. Wanamaker, Eugene Fitch Ware, Cy Warman, James W. Wartmann, James Eli Watson, M.V. Watson, LeRoy Titus Weeks, Josephine S. Weiler, T.D. Wells, James Terry White, William Allen White, Elizabeth Lockhart Wickliffe, George Washington Wiggs, C. Ernest Williams, Charles Richard Williams, Chauncey Lawrence Williams, Anna E. Williamson, Erasmus Wilson, Francis Wilson, Isidore Witmark, James H. Woodard, Mrs. M.H. Woodard, Charles Ainsworth Woodard, W.H. Wright.
Other materials in the collection include: Children's letters and writings (1897-1914, 32 items); Memorabilia (14 items); Miscellaneous (Empty envelopes; Lists of belongings of the late JWR, 1917; Lists of poems for reading by JWR; Lists of poems by JWR for publishing purposes; Tour receipts and schedules of JWR, 1885-1900); Photographs (32 Photographs of Riley and his homes; Photographs of Albert Jeremiah Beveridge, Julia Marlowe, William Allen White); Printed materials (Clippings related to JWR; Poems by JWR).
Following the Riley writings are five folders of copies of letters to James Whitcomb Riley and his writings, the originals of which were offered by Lesley Payne to several university libraries and are not present in the Lilly Library. These are for reference use only.
Related Material
See Riley mss., Riley mss. II, Riley mss. III, Riley mss. IV, and Riley mss. VI, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 1977
American Literature--Indiana
- Correspondence
  - 1876-1889, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1890-1896, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1897-1898, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1899-1901, (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Putnam, Frank Arthur. To Riley, James Whitcomb, 17 November 1900 (Box 16)
  - 1902, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1903-1904, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1905-1906, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1907, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1908, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1909-1910, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1911-1912, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1913-1916, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Undated A-Z, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Burnett, Frances Eliza (Hodgson), Greeting on birch, undated (Box 15)
- Children's Letters
  - 1897-1907 (Box 13)
  - (Marion Hunter Weinstein + Faith Baldwin), 1908-1914 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous
  - Lists by JWR for publishing poems (Box 13)
  - Lists by JWR for reading (Box 13)
  - Memorabilia (Box 13)
  - Tour receipts and schedules of JWR, 1885-1900 (Box 13)
  - Lists of belongings of JWR, 1917 (Box 13)
  - Empty envelopes (Box 13)
- Printed
  - Poems by JWR (Box 13)
  - Clippings (Box 13)
- Photographs
  - JWR and his home (Box 13)
  - Photographs of others: AJ Beriridge, Julia Marlowe, William H. White (Box 13)
- Writings
  - Poems, A-Z, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Copies
  - Correspondence, 1882-1927 (Box 3)
  - Alderman Library, University of Virginia (Box 3)
  - Huntington Library (Box 3)
  - Piermont Morgan Library (Box 3)
  - Poems (Box 3)